<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Drupal CMS</title>
    <description>Stay informed about developments in Drupal CMS.</description>
    <link>https://www.drupal.org/project/drupal-cms</link>
    <item>
      <title>#3574664: The `site:export` command should be able to export on top of another recipe</title>
      <link>https://github.com/dbuytaert/drupal-digests/blob/main/issues/drupal-cms/3574664.md</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">drupal-cms-3574664</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 21:09:40 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Project:&lt;/strong&gt; Drupal CMS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Type:&lt;/strong&gt; Normal feature request&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Status:&lt;/strong&gt; Fixed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Diff:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://git.drupalcode.org/project/drupal_cms/-/commit/4c57de393c8eb0db9a16ed46263c402979cdf5d9"&gt;4c57de3&lt;/a&gt; · +120/-14 prod · +134/-10 test · 10 files&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Discussion:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.drupal.org/node/3574664"&gt;#3574664&lt;/a&gt; · 1 contributor · 9 comments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drupal CMS now makes it easier to create and publish custom site templates. When exporting your site as a recipe, you can copy scaffolding from a base template that includes important files like CI configuration, license, and README. The export command also fixes common problems that appeared when building site templates, such as issues with front page paths using internal IDs instead of aliases and menu links not properly tracking their parent relationships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Impact&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No upgrade or configuration changes required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Technical details&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;drush site:export&lt;/code&gt; command now accepts a &lt;code&gt;--base&lt;/code&gt; option that mirrors a base recipe directory into the destination before exporting. This uses Symfony Filesystem to copy files while excluding the &lt;code&gt;content&lt;/code&gt; directory and VCS files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Three bug fixes were added to improve the reliability of site exports. First, &lt;code&gt;GenericConfigurationListener&lt;/code&gt; now converts the front page path in &lt;code&gt;system.site&lt;/code&gt; config from a system path like &lt;code&gt;/node/6&lt;/code&gt; to its alias using &lt;code&gt;AliasManagerInterface&lt;/code&gt;. This works around &lt;a href="https://www.drupal.org/node/1503146"&gt;#1503146&lt;/a&gt; until it's released in core. The class gained a &lt;code&gt;$convertFrontPagePathToAlias&lt;/code&gt; property that &lt;code&gt;SiteExporter&lt;/code&gt; sets to TRUE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, &lt;code&gt;DefaultContentSubscriber&lt;/code&gt; now ensures menu link content entities depend on their parent menu links during export. When &lt;code&gt;PreExportEvent&lt;/code&gt; is fired for a &lt;code&gt;MenuLinkContentInterface&lt;/code&gt;, the subscriber extracts the parent UUID from the plugin ID and loads the parent entity via &lt;code&gt;EntityRepositoryInterface&lt;/code&gt;, then adds it as a dependency. This shims around &lt;a href="https://www.drupal.org/node/3562072"&gt;#3562072&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, the command now checks if the destination directory exists and returns a failure status if it does, preventing accidental overwrites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Test coverage was expanded with &lt;code&gt;testExportSiteWithBase()&lt;/code&gt; to verify the base recipe copying behavior, and &lt;code&gt;testExportSite()&lt;/code&gt; was enhanced to validate the front page alias conversion and menu link dependency fixes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Timeline&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Opened: February 19, 2026&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Committed: February 19, 2026&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Collaboration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;phenaproxima created this issue, implemented the feature, and merged it into both 2.x and 2.0.x branches the same day it was opened. The work responds directly to feedback from Andy at Dripyard about bugs affecting site template creators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This summary is AI-generated and may contain errors. Check the &lt;a href="https://www.drupal.org/node/3574664"&gt;original issue on Drupal.org&lt;/a&gt; for the full picture. For more digests, see &lt;a href="https://github.com/dbuytaert/drupal-digests/"&gt;Drupal Digests&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>#3573304: Create a 'Blank' template option for users who want to start from scratch</title>
      <link>https://github.com/dbuytaert/drupal-digests/blob/main/issues/drupal-cms/3573304.md</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">drupal-cms-3573304</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 15:53:41 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Project:&lt;/strong&gt; Drupal CMS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Type:&lt;/strong&gt; Normal feature request&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Status:&lt;/strong&gt; Fixed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Diff:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://git.drupalcode.org/project/drupal_cms/-/commit/85790f55005f481e301667998f4d5e251b4afece"&gt;85790f5&lt;/a&gt; · +56/-78 prod · +10/-10 test · 16 files&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Discussion:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.drupal.org/node/3573304"&gt;#3573304&lt;/a&gt; · 4 contributors · 24 comments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drupal CMS now offers a &amp;quot;Blank&amp;quot; template option during installation for users who want to start with a minimal foundation. This template provides Drupal CMS's baseline functionality without the Mercury design system or component library, giving developers complete freedom to build their own design approach. The blank template includes an automatically generated minimal theme with just header, content, and footer regions, plus a single blank Canvas page as the home page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Impact&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No upgrade or configuration changes required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Technical details&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The blank template is implemented by making &lt;code&gt;drupal_cms_site_template_base&lt;/code&gt; visible and usable during installation. Previously, this site template was hidden from the installer UI and only available to developers via command line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The implementation leverages the &lt;code&gt;site_template_helper&lt;/code&gt; Composer plugin to dynamically generate a minimal theme called &amp;quot;blank&amp;quot; when the template is installed. This theme is based on core's &lt;code&gt;starterkit_theme&lt;/code&gt; but includes only three regions: header, content, and footer. The theme generation happens automatically at &lt;code&gt;composer require&lt;/code&gt; time through plugin configuration in the site template's &lt;code&gt;composer.json&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;drupal_cms_installer_install_tasks_alter()&lt;/code&gt; function was simplified by removing the &lt;code&gt;SiteTemplateFormAlter&lt;/code&gt; class that previously hid &lt;code&gt;drupal_cms_site_template_base&lt;/code&gt; from the installer. The template now appears alongside other options like Starter and the various prebuilt templates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The installer UI received CSS improvements to accommodate the additional template option, switching from a fixed three-column grid to a responsive grid that adapts from two to four columns based on viewport width. The &lt;code&gt;SiteExporter&lt;/code&gt; service was updated to remove development-only dependencies like &lt;code&gt;site_template_helper&lt;/code&gt; when exporting site configurations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The blank template includes a single empty Canvas page set as the front page to avoid a 404 on first visit. It also includes the utility page content type through &lt;code&gt;drupal_cms_content_type_base&lt;/code&gt;, which provides the Canvas page functionality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Timeline&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Opened: February 13, 2026&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First commit: February 16, 2026 (3 days later)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Last commit: February 18, 2026 (2 days later)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Collaboration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;phenaproxima implemented the technical approach after pameeela identified the need and lauriii provided requirements feedback. phenaproxima resurrected and integrated the &lt;code&gt;site_template_helper&lt;/code&gt; plugin to enable dynamic theme generation, solving the challenge of scaffolding a minimal theme without maintaining another static theme in the codebase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Lessons learned&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When generating scaffolding at dependency installation time, use Composer plugins to run generation scripts. This allows site templates to create themes dynamically from starter kits without maintaining static copies that drift out of sync with upstream. &lt;em&gt;(via phenaproxima)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When designing starter templates, distinguish between customization that users might want versus customization they definitely need. Ship pre-built themes for optional customization, but generate minimal scaffolds for scenarios where users must customize. &lt;em&gt;(via phenaproxima)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This summary is AI-generated and may contain errors. Check the &lt;a href="https://www.drupal.org/node/3573304"&gt;original issue on Drupal.org&lt;/a&gt; for the full picture. For more digests, see &lt;a href="https://github.com/dbuytaert/drupal-digests/"&gt;Drupal Digests&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>#3573537: Updated method of suppressing the Content menu doesn't work as expected</title>
      <link>https://github.com/dbuytaert/drupal-digests/blob/main/issues/drupal-cms/3573537.md</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">drupal-cms-3573537</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 03:45:24 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Project:&lt;/strong&gt; Drupal CMS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Type:&lt;/strong&gt; Normal bug report&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Status:&lt;/strong&gt; Fixed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Diff:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://git.drupalcode.org/project/drupal_cms/-/commit/1556d3cafa8ff17bbd1aadccee805c46967309bb"&gt;1556d3c&lt;/a&gt; · +36/-36 prod · +60/-0 test · 12 files&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Discussion:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.drupal.org/node/3573537"&gt;#3573537&lt;/a&gt; · 2 contributors · 16 comments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drupal CMS was showing unwanted &amp;quot;Create&amp;quot; menu links in the navigation menu for each content type that was added to the site. A previous refactoring had moved the suppression logic from code into configuration files, but this approach made the links reappear for any new content types created after installation. The fix moves the suppression logic back into code as a temporary polyfill until core addresses the underlying usability issues with the navigation menu's &amp;quot;Create&amp;quot; section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Impact&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No upgrade or configuration changes required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Technical details&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Navigation module in Drupal core automatically creates menu links for creating content under a &lt;code&gt;navigation.create&lt;/code&gt; parent menu item. Drupal CMS previously suppressed these links using &lt;code&gt;hook_menu_links_discovered_alter()&lt;/code&gt; in the &lt;code&gt;drupal_cms_helper&lt;/code&gt; module. During a refactoring to consolidate polyfills, this logic was replaced with configuration overrides in recipe files using the &lt;code&gt;overrideMenuLinks&lt;/code&gt; config action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The configuration-based approach had a critical limitation: it could only disable specific menu links that existed at the time the recipe was applied. Any content types or media types created after installation would generate new navigation links that were not covered by the configuration, causing them to appear unexpectedly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fix restores the original code-based approach by adding &lt;code&gt;alterDiscoveredMenuLinks()&lt;/code&gt; to the &lt;code&gt;PluginHooks&lt;/code&gt; class in &lt;code&gt;drupal_cms_helper&lt;/code&gt;. This hook implementation runs after the Navigation module's own hook (enforced with &lt;code&gt;OrderAfter(['navigation'])&lt;/code&gt;) and disables all menu links with the &lt;code&gt;navigation.create&lt;/code&gt; parent, plus the parent link itself. This ensures all current and future &amp;quot;Create&amp;quot; links are suppressed dynamically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The polyfill includes a &lt;code&gt;@todo&lt;/code&gt; referencing &lt;a href="https://www.drupal.org/project/drupal/issues/3573730"&gt;#3573730&lt;/a&gt; where core will address the underlying usability concerns. All configuration overrides for navigation menu links were removed from the &lt;code&gt;drupal_cms_admin_ui&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;drupal_cms_content_type_base&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;drupal_cms_media&lt;/code&gt; recipe files. Test coverage was added to verify that dynamically created content types have their navigation links properly suppressed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Timeline&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Opened: February 14, 2026&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Committed: February 18, 2026 (4 days later)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Collaboration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;pameeela reported the issue and advocated strongly for keeping this as a code-based polyfill rather than configuration, making the important point that configuration changes in site templates would be impossible to unwind. phenaproxima implemented the fix and engaged in thoughtful discussion about the tradeoffs between polyfills and explicit UX decisions, ultimately agreeing to restore the code-based approach after confirming the decision over Zoom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Lessons learned&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When implementing a temporary fix for an upstream issue, prefer code-based solutions over configuration changes. Code can be removed cleanly when the upstream fix arrives, while configuration changes persist in user sites and require complex update paths to unwind. &lt;em&gt;(via pameeela, phenaproxima)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When the direction of an upstream fix is unclear, avoid assuming your temporary workaround matches the eventual solution. Document the dependency explicitly, but recognize that alignment with the final approach may require later refactoring regardless of implementation strategy. &lt;em&gt;(via phenaproxima)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This summary is AI-generated and may contain errors. Check the &lt;a href="https://www.drupal.org/node/3573537"&gt;original issue on Drupal.org&lt;/a&gt; for the full picture. For more digests, see &lt;a href="https://github.com/dbuytaert/drupal-digests/"&gt;Drupal Digests&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>#3573714: Add and update AI tools docs page, and update the SEO docs</title>
      <link>https://github.com/dbuytaert/drupal-digests/blob/main/issues/drupal-cms/3573714.md</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">drupal-cms-3573714</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 15:18:16 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Project:&lt;/strong&gt; Drupal CMS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Type:&lt;/strong&gt; Normal task&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Status:&lt;/strong&gt; Fixed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Diff:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://git.drupalcode.org/project/drupal_cms/-/commit/5567a4291bcbd538f3965f93d430c7ddae865476"&gt;5567a42&lt;/a&gt; · +89/-26 · 5 files&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Discussion:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.drupal.org/node/3573714"&gt;#3573714&lt;/a&gt; · 3 contributors · 11 comments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Documentation for Drupal CMS now includes a dedicated page explaining AI tools and how to use them for content creation and site administration. The AI assistant can generate accessible image descriptions, help navigate configuration options, and assist with building features like content types and taxonomies. The SEO documentation has also been updated to reflect that the HTML Sitemap module was removed from Drupal CMS 2.0, focusing instead on the XML sitemap for search engines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Impact&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No upgrade or configuration changes required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Technical details&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This change adds a new documentation file at &lt;code&gt;docs/src/customize/ai-tools.md&lt;/code&gt; that describes Drupal CMS's AI features including the AI assistant chatbot and automated alternate text generation for images. The documentation covers installation steps for the AI Assistant add-on, configuration for three supported providers (amazee.ai, Anthropic, and OpenAI), and practical examples of using AI tools for navigation, content tasks, and feature scaffolding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The existing SEO documentation in &lt;code&gt;docs/src/promote/essentials.md&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;docs/src/promote/install.md&lt;/code&gt; was updated to remove references to the HTML Sitemap module, which is no longer part of Drupal CMS 2.0. The updated docs clarify that Simple XML Sitemap is the tool for search engine indexing, and several broken links were corrected throughout the SEO documentation files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Timeline&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Opened: February 15, 2026&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Committed: February 17, 2026 (1 day later)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Collaboration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pameeela created the initial version of the AI tools documentation and fixed broken links in the SEO section. Thejimbirch reviewed the changes, identified that the SEO documentation updates related to the HTML Sitemap removal belonged in scope for this issue, and updated the issue title to reflect the expanded scope before moving it to ready for review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This summary is AI-generated and may contain errors. Check the &lt;a href="https://www.drupal.org/node/3573714"&gt;original issue on Drupal.org&lt;/a&gt; for the full picture. For more digests, see &lt;a href="https://github.com/dbuytaert/drupal-digests/"&gt;Drupal Digests&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>#3574009: Add a hidden Drush command to export all content</title>
      <link>https://github.com/dbuytaert/drupal-digests/blob/main/issues/drupal-cms/3574009.md</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">drupal-cms-3574009</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 15:16:32 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Project:&lt;/strong&gt; Drupal CMS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Type:&lt;/strong&gt; Normal feature request&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Status:&lt;/strong&gt; Fixed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Diff:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://git.drupalcode.org/project/drupal_cms/-/commit/8a6b09bacd4a25dca24ba392ea9a63754131c5c7"&gt;8a6b09b&lt;/a&gt; · +256/-66 prod · +20/-4 test · 12 files&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Discussion:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.drupal.org/node/3574009"&gt;#3574009&lt;/a&gt; · 1 contributor · 6 comments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drupal CMS now includes a hidden Drush command that makes it easy for developers to export all content from a site to a directory. This is useful for creating development snapshots, migrating content between environments, or backing up site content in a portable format. The command is hidden because it's intended for developer use rather than routine site administration. The change also extracts the content loading logic into a reusable component that both the site export and content export commands can use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Impact&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No upgrade or configuration changes required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Technical details&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This change adds a new &lt;code&gt;content:export:all&lt;/code&gt; Drush command in the &lt;code&gt;drupal_cms_helper&lt;/code&gt; module. The command is marked as hidden (not shown in normal help listings) and exports all content entities to a specified directory using Drupal's default content export system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The implementation extracts the content loading logic from &lt;code&gt;SiteExporter::loadAllContent()&lt;/code&gt; into a new &lt;code&gt;ContentLoader&lt;/code&gt; class that implements &lt;code&gt;IteratorAggregate&lt;/code&gt;. The &lt;code&gt;ContentLoader&lt;/code&gt; iterates through all entity types, filters out internal entities and path aliases, and yields all content entities. It excludes users 0 and 1 since those always exist with the same IDs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new &lt;code&gt;ExportAllContentCommand&lt;/code&gt; class uses the &lt;code&gt;Exporter&lt;/code&gt; service to export each entity with its dependencies to the target directory. The command accepts a single required argument for the destination directory path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both &lt;code&gt;ContentLoader&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;ExportAllContentCommand&lt;/code&gt; are marked as &lt;code&gt;@internal&lt;/code&gt;, but the command itself is marked as &lt;code&gt;@api&lt;/code&gt; to signal that developers can rely on it. The change also adds &lt;code&gt;@api&lt;/code&gt; annotations to existing commands (&lt;code&gt;content:import&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;site:export&lt;/code&gt;) to clarify their stability guarantees within Drupal CMS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Timeline&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Opened: February 17, 2026&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Committed: February 17, 2026&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Collaboration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;phenaproxima identified the use case and implemented the feature in a single day, including extracting the shared content loading logic into a reusable component and updating the existing site export functionality to use it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This summary is AI-generated and may contain errors. Check the &lt;a href="https://www.drupal.org/node/3574009"&gt;original issue on Drupal.org&lt;/a&gt; for the full picture. For more digests, see &lt;a href="https://github.com/dbuytaert/drupal-digests/"&gt;Drupal Digests&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>#3564710: Add a `--generic` option to `drush config:export`</title>
      <link>https://github.com/dbuytaert/drupal-digests/blob/main/issues/drupal-cms/3564710.md</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">drupal-cms-3564710</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 16:10:05 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Project:&lt;/strong&gt; Drupal CMS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Type:&lt;/strong&gt; Normal feature request&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Status:&lt;/strong&gt; Fixed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Diff:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://git.drupalcode.org/project/drupal_cms/-/commit/22d5dd386f93fdc25ffa139fbe22956b0a6714a2"&gt;22d5dd3&lt;/a&gt; · +316/-190 prod · +134/-0 test · 16 files&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Discussion:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.drupal.org/node/3564710"&gt;#3564710&lt;/a&gt; · 1 contributor · 6 comments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When exporting configuration to create a recipe or site template, you previously had to manually remove &lt;code&gt;uuid&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;_core&lt;/code&gt; keys from the exported files. This is tedious and easy to forget. The &lt;code&gt;drupal_cms_helper&lt;/code&gt; module now provides a &lt;code&gt;--generic&lt;/code&gt; option for the &lt;code&gt;drush config:export&lt;/code&gt; command that automatically strips these keys, making exported configuration ready to use in recipes without manual cleanup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Impact&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No upgrade or configuration changes required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Technical details&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;drupal_cms_helper&lt;/code&gt; module adds a &lt;code&gt;--generic&lt;/code&gt; option to Drush's &lt;code&gt;config:export&lt;/code&gt; command. When this flag is set, a new &lt;code&gt;ConfigExportCommandListener&lt;/code&gt; class hooks into Drush's console events to register a &lt;code&gt;GenericConfigurationListener&lt;/code&gt; with the &lt;code&gt;ConfigEvents::STORAGE_TRANSFORM_EXPORT&lt;/code&gt; event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;GenericConfigurationListener&lt;/code&gt; processes each exported configuration object and removes the &lt;code&gt;_core&lt;/code&gt; key universally. For the &lt;code&gt;uuid&lt;/code&gt; key, it uses logic from &lt;code&gt;EntityTypeManagerInterface&lt;/code&gt; to determine whether the UUID should be kept. UUIDs are preserved only when they serve as the entity ID (like Canvas folders), but removed in all other cases including simple configuration and standard config entities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The existing &lt;code&gt;SiteExporter&lt;/code&gt; service was refactored to use this same listener instead of the previous &lt;code&gt;SiteExportFileStorage&lt;/code&gt; class, which has been removed. This consolidates the generic configuration logic into a single reusable event listener. The &lt;code&gt;SiteExporter&lt;/code&gt; now uses &lt;code&gt;config.storage.export&lt;/code&gt; and attaches the &lt;code&gt;GenericConfigurationListener&lt;/code&gt; when exporting sites as recipes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Test coverage includes functional tests that verify both generic and non-generic exports produce the correct output, checking both config entities and simple configuration objects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Timeline&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Opened: December 24, 2025&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Committed: February 11, 2026 (1 month later)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This summary is AI-generated and may contain errors. Check the &lt;a href="https://www.drupal.org/node/3564710"&gt;original issue on Drupal.org&lt;/a&gt; for the full picture. For more digests, see &lt;a href="https://github.com/dbuytaert/drupal-digests/"&gt;Drupal Digests&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>#3569627: Disable Amazee AI auto-trial provisioning in drupal_cms_ai tests</title>
      <link>https://github.com/dbuytaert/drupal-digests/blob/main/issues/drupal-cms/3569627.md</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">drupal-cms-3569627</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 13:54:31 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Project:&lt;/strong&gt; Drupal CMS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Type:&lt;/strong&gt; Critical bug report&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Status:&lt;/strong&gt; Fixed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Diff:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://git.drupalcode.org/project/drupal_cms/-/commit/949dfb6b26c11c6f4e714fa047d2de32d483b909"&gt;949dfb6&lt;/a&gt; · +2/-2 prod · +30/-12 test · 6 files&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Discussion:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.drupal.org/node/3569627"&gt;#3569627&lt;/a&gt; · 4 contributors · 20 comments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Drupal CMS AI tests ran, they tried to create real trial accounts with Amazee.ai by making API calls. These calls timed out after 30 seconds, causing tests to fail. The issue also created unwanted trial accounts on Amazee's systems. The fix detects test environments and skips the trial provisioning step automatically, making tests run faster and preventing spurious account creation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Impact&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No upgrade or configuration changes required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Technical details&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;drupal_cms_ai&lt;/code&gt; recipe includes the &lt;code&gt;ai_provider_amazeeio&lt;/code&gt; module, which automatically provisions trial API access when applied. The &lt;code&gt;ensureAmazeeAiAccess&lt;/code&gt; config action triggered &lt;code&gt;TrialAccountProvisioner&lt;/code&gt; during recipe application, making HTTP requests to &lt;code&gt;https://api.amazee.ai/auth/generate-trial-access&lt;/code&gt;. In test environments these requests timed out after 30 seconds, failing &lt;code&gt;ComponentValidationTest&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The initial fix temporarily skipped the test on CI using &lt;code&gt;getenv('CI')&lt;/code&gt;. The permanent solution came from upgrading &lt;code&gt;ai_provider_amazeeio&lt;/code&gt; from version 1.2.6 to 1.2.7. The new version of the module adds environment detection to &lt;code&gt;TrialAccountProvisioner&lt;/code&gt; that recognizes test contexts and skips provisioning. This happens through a &lt;code&gt;ai_provider_amazeeio.trial_access_provisioning.disable&lt;/code&gt; container parameter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The test now validates that provisioning is disabled by checking that output strings like &amp;quot;Waiting for API response&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;Provisioning amazee.ai trial account...&amp;quot; do not appear, and by asserting the container parameter is true. Test runtime dropped from 30+ seconds of timeout waiting to approximately 140 seconds for the full test.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Timeline&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Opened: January 26, 2026&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First commit: January 26, 2026&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Last commit: February 9, 2026 (13 days later)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Collaboration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fix required coordination across two projects. Marcus Johansson identified option #2 from the proposed solutions as the best approach and opened &lt;a href="https://www.drupal.org/project/ai_provider_amazeeio/issues/3569665"&gt;#3569665&lt;/a&gt; in the ai_provider_amazeeio module. Dan2k3k4 implemented and released version 1.2.7 with the environment detection. Phenaproxima provided the temporary skip to unblock CI, then re-enabled the test and verified no actual provisioning occurred. This pattern of coordinating fixes across dependent projects while using temporary workarounds to keep tests passing worked well for a critical issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Lessons learned&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When code performs external operations during installation (API calls, account provisioning), it should detect test environments and no-op to avoid side effects. Check for test context at the operation's entry point rather than deep in the stack or via fixture modules. &lt;em&gt;(via mxr576, marcus_johansson)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This summary is AI-generated and may contain errors. Check the &lt;a href="https://www.drupal.org/node/3569627"&gt;original issue on Drupal.org&lt;/a&gt; for the full picture. For more digests, see &lt;a href="https://github.com/dbuytaert/drupal-digests/"&gt;Drupal Digests&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>#3569529: Add an AGENTS.md file</title>
      <link>https://github.com/dbuytaert/drupal-digests/blob/main/issues/drupal-cms/3569529.md</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">drupal-cms-3569529</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 17:24:31 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Project:&lt;/strong&gt; Drupal CMS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Type:&lt;/strong&gt; Normal feature request&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Status:&lt;/strong&gt; Fixed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Diff:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://git.drupalcode.org/project/drupal_cms/-/commit/aecaffbe229e6296ba2092a2bc073b2f2b7807dc"&gt;aecaffb&lt;/a&gt; · +264/-0 prod · +4/-0 infra · 10 files&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Discussion:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.drupal.org/node/3569529"&gt;#3569529&lt;/a&gt; · 4 contributors · 12 comments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drupal CMS now includes an AGENTS.md file to help AI coding assistants work more effectively with the codebase. This file provides structured guidance on the project's technology stack, coding standards, development commands, and prohibited actions. The documentation helps AI tools avoid common mistakes and follow project conventions when assisting developers with Drupal CMS contributions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Impact&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No upgrade or configuration changes required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Technical details&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new &lt;code&gt;AGENTS.md&lt;/code&gt; file documents Drupal CMS-specific conventions for AI coding assistants. It covers the monorepo structure with recipes in the &lt;code&gt;recipes&lt;/code&gt; directory, the &lt;code&gt;drupal_cms_helper&lt;/code&gt; module, and the &lt;code&gt;project_template&lt;/code&gt; directory used for end-user installations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The file provides command references for common development tasks using DDEV and Drush, including recipe application, PHPUnit testing, site installation, and content export with &lt;code&gt;drush content:export&lt;/code&gt;. It specifies coding standards like using strict typing, the &lt;code&gt;?type&lt;/code&gt; nullable syntax, &lt;code&gt;#[\Override]&lt;/code&gt; attributes, and marking new classes as final with private members.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several README files in protected directories (&lt;code&gt;cpanel_template&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;patches&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;scripts&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;splitter&lt;/code&gt;) now explicitly warn agents not to modify those areas. The prohibited actions section lists destructive operations like running &lt;code&gt;ddev tag&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;composer update&lt;/code&gt; outside the project root, and prevents agents from adding patches or pinning dependencies in Composer files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The documentation emphasizes defensive programming in &lt;code&gt;drupal_cms_helper&lt;/code&gt;, requiring checks like &lt;code&gt;\Drupal::moduleHandler()-&amp;gt;moduleExists()&lt;/code&gt; before using optional module functionality. It also instructs agents to mark new non-test classes as internal with specific warning text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Timeline&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Opened: January 26, 2026&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Committed: February 4, 2026 (9 days later)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Collaboration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This issue demonstrates the Drupal CMS team's pragmatic approach to AI tooling. The issue author acknowledged ambivalence about AI while recognizing its practical utility and the need to accommodate developers using these tools. Multiple contributors provided feedback to improve structure and readability, with discussion about whether to manage the file through a separate package like the scaffold system. The team decided keeping &lt;code&gt;AGENTS.md&lt;/code&gt; in the repository made more sense for documenting internal workings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This summary is AI-generated and may contain errors. Check the &lt;a href="https://www.drupal.org/node/3569529"&gt;original issue on Drupal.org&lt;/a&gt; for the full picture. For more digests, see &lt;a href="https://github.com/dbuytaert/drupal-digests/"&gt;Drupal Digests&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>#3568955: Update documentation for 2.0 release</title>
      <link>https://github.com/dbuytaert/drupal-digests/blob/main/issues/drupal-cms/3568955.md</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">drupal-cms-3568955</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 15:28:39 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Project:&lt;/strong&gt; Drupal CMS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Type:&lt;/strong&gt; Normal task&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Status:&lt;/strong&gt; Fixed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Diff:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://git.drupalcode.org/project/drupal_cms/-/commit/5a8c498464b1bee8422feb43d157e888df9f55ad"&gt;5a8c498&lt;/a&gt; · +1119/-2269 · 130 files&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Discussion:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.drupal.org/node/3568955"&gt;#3568955&lt;/a&gt; · 2 contributors · 13 comments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drupal CMS 2.0 brings a major documentation refresh to help site builders and content editors find what they need faster. The documentation has been reorganized with a clearer structure, splitting &amp;quot;Create&amp;quot; content into &amp;quot;Get Started,&amp;quot; &amp;quot;Customize,&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;Manage&amp;quot; sections. Many outdated tutorials have been removed or rewritten, screenshots updated, and navigation paths corrected to reflect the 2.0 interface. The changes make it easier to discover features like recommended add-ons, accessibility tools, email setup, hosting guidance, and content management workflows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Impact&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No upgrade or configuration changes required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Technical details&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This issue consolidated documentation updates for the Drupal CMS 2.0 release across multiple merge requests. The changes reorganized the information architecture by moving files between directories: content from &lt;code&gt;docs/src/create/&lt;/code&gt; was redistributed to &lt;code&gt;docs/src/get-started/&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;docs/src/customize/&lt;/code&gt;, and in some cases removed entirely. Files moved to &lt;code&gt;customize/&lt;/code&gt; include add-ons, modules, email setup, hosting, consent management, and privacy policy documentation. New content in &lt;code&gt;get-started/&lt;/code&gt; covers site settings and theme customization. Several tutorials were deleted, including workflows, site-settings, and detailed navigation guidance, while others were significantly condensed. The contributor removed verbose &amp;quot;Goal,&amp;quot; &amp;quot;Prerequisites,&amp;quot; &amp;quot;Next steps,&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;Wrap-up&amp;quot; sections from most tutorials to streamline the content. Screenshots were updated throughout to reflect the 2.0 administrative interface, and admin paths were corrected (switching from old-style notation to the newer format). The changes also removed references to features not present in 2.0, such as the Events content type, and updated feature descriptions to match current functionality. Binary image files were deleted or replaced as part of the refresh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Timeline&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Opened: January 22, 2026&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First commit: February 2, 2026 (11 days later)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Last commit: February 4, 2026 (2 days later)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Collaboration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This documentation refresh was a collaborative effort between pameeela and phenaproxima over two weeks with three commits. The approach of merging updates in stages made reviews more manageable. Pameeela created the initial merge request and noted it was &amp;quot;better than what we have&amp;quot; even before completion, allowing incremental improvement. After the first merge, pameeela continued refining and reviewed every documentation page before submitting a second merge request. Phenaproxima handled merging to the 2.x branch and cherry-picking necessary changes back to the 2.0.x release branch. This iterative process demonstrates how large documentation projects can be broken into reviewable chunks while still achieving comprehensive coverage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This summary is AI-generated and may contain errors. Check the &lt;a href="https://www.drupal.org/node/3568955"&gt;original issue on Drupal.org&lt;/a&gt; for the full picture. For more digests, see &lt;a href="https://github.com/dbuytaert/drupal-digests/"&gt;Drupal Digests&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>#3571163: Add a CONTRIBUTING.md to the project template</title>
      <link>https://github.com/dbuytaert/drupal-digests/blob/main/issues/drupal-cms/3571163.md</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">drupal-cms-3571163</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 02:37:34 +0000</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Project:&lt;/strong&gt; Drupal CMS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Type:&lt;/strong&gt; Normal feature request&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Status:&lt;/strong&gt; Fixed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Diff:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://git.drupalcode.org/project/drupal_cms/-/commit/8f92852874403c3971d9b1fe1ebf746d29087095"&gt;8f92852&lt;/a&gt; · +46/-12 · 4 files&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Discussion:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.drupal.org/node/3571163"&gt;#3571163&lt;/a&gt; · 2 contributors · 7 comments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drupal CMS now includes a dedicated CONTRIBUTING.md file that guides potential contributors through the setup process. People who wanted to contribute were cloning the wrong repository and getting stuck because there was no clear documentation. The new file explains the monorepo structure, provides step-by-step DDEV installation instructions, and links to the development issue queue and Slack channel. The README.md was also updated to point to this new contributor guide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Impact&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No upgrade or configuration changes required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Technical details&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Drupal CMS project template now includes a &lt;code&gt;CONTRIBUTING.md&lt;/code&gt; file in the &lt;code&gt;project_template/&lt;/code&gt; directory. This file addresses a recurring problem where contributors would clone the published Composer package repository instead of the development repository.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new &lt;code&gt;CONTRIBUTING.md&lt;/code&gt; explains that Drupal CMS uses a monorepo structure that automatically splits into smaller projects. It specifies DDEV version 1.24.0 or later as a requirement and provides three commands to get started: clone the repository from &lt;code&gt;git@git.drupal.org:project/drupal_cms.git&lt;/code&gt;, change into the directory, and run &lt;code&gt;ddev launch&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The file also documents common DDEV commands like &lt;code&gt;ddev drush&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;ddev composer&lt;/code&gt;, and directs contributors to open issues and merge requests in the Drupal CMS development issue queue. It includes links to the code of conduct, the &lt;code&gt;#drupal-cms-development&lt;/code&gt; Slack channel, and DDEV documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;README.md&lt;/code&gt; was refactored to remove redundant contribution information and now references &lt;code&gt;CONTRIBUTING.md&lt;/code&gt; instead. The &amp;quot;Contributing&amp;quot; section was renamed to &amp;quot;Contributing &amp;amp; Support&amp;quot; and streamlined to focus on reporting issues and getting support, with a link to the new contributor guide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Timeline&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Opened: February 3, 2026&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Committed: February 3, 2026&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This summary is AI-generated and may contain errors. Check the &lt;a href="https://www.drupal.org/node/3571163"&gt;original issue on Drupal.org&lt;/a&gt; for the full picture. For more digests, see &lt;a href="https://github.com/dbuytaert/drupal-digests/"&gt;Drupal Digests&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>